The bodies of loops can contain any statement including other loops.
بدنه چرخه ها میتواند هر عبارتی را شامل شود از جمله چرخه های دیگر را.
We'll explore that in this lecture. Here we have a loop inside another loop.
در این مبحث این مطلب را تحقیق میکنیم.در اینجا چرخه ای را در درون چرخه ای دیگر داریم.
The outer loop has I range over the values ten, eleven, and twelve, And for each of
چرخه بیرونی دارای دامنهi ده،یازده،و دوازده است،و برای هر یک از
those iterations j is going to range through one, two, three, and four.
این دوره گردشها j دامنه اش یک،دو،سه،و چهار است.
When I visualize this I starts off referring to the value of ten.
وقتی که این را مجسم میکنم با  مقدار ده شروع میکنم.
J doesn't exist yet because we have just reached the four loop the first time.
j هنوز وجود ندارد زیرا تازه برای اولین بار به چرخهfor رسیده ایم.
This inner four loop. J is going to take on the value one in the
این چرخه for داخلی.j در اولین دور چرخش مقدار یک را به خود میگیرد.
first iteration. I still refers to ten, And we're about to
i هنوز ده هست،و قصد داریم که ij را
print IJ, so we should see ten and one up here.
چاپ کنیم،پس باید که ده و یک را اینجا ببینیم.
Notice that as soon as we printed tenant one, we went back to line two, not to line
توجه داشته باشید که همین که ده و یک را چاپ کردیم،برگشتیم به سطر دو،نه سطر یک.
one. And the reason for that is we are going to
و دلیل آن اینکه میخواهیم
completely execute this inner four loop until J has gone through the numbers 1,2,3
به طور کامل این چرخه for داخلی را پردازش کنیم تا اینکه j اعداد 1و2و3 و4 را کارسازی کند.
and four. So that means that J will take on the
پس معنی اش این است که j دفعه بعد مقدار دو را به خود میگیرد.
value two next. And we're going to print tenant two.
و میخواهیم که ده و دو را چاپ کنیم.
Now J is going to take on the value three, J now refers to three, and we'll print
اکنون j عدد سه را به خود یگیرد،و ده وسه و چهار را چاپ خواهیم کرد.
tenant three and four. Now we are done with this inner four loop, and so we are
اکنون کارمان با این چرخه for داخلی تمام شد،و میخواهیم که
going to jump back out to line one because we have completed execution of the body of
بپریم به سطر یک زیرا که کار پردازش بدنه خارجی چرخه for را پایان دادیم.
the outer four loop. Now, I is going to take on the value
اکنون i مقدار یازده را به خود میگیرد.
eleven. J is going to take on the values one, two,
j مقادیر 1,2,3,4را دوباره به خود میگیرد.
three, and four again. And now we're done with this inner loop,
و اکنون کارمان با چرخه داخلی تمام شده،
so we'll go back out to the outer one. Now, we will do the last iteration of the
بنابراین برمیگردیم به چرخه بیرونی.اکنون،آخرین دور گردش چرخه بیرونی را انجام میدهیم.
outer loop. Alright, it starts off as twelve and J is
خوب،میشود دوازده و
going to go through the numbers one two three and four again.
j  دوباره اعداد1و2و3و4 را به خود میگیرد.
And I will not change again. Now we are done with this inner loop.
و دیگر عوضش نمیکنم.اکنون کار چرخه داخلی را تمام کردیم
We go back and check the outer loop once more.
برمیگردیم و یکبار دیگر چرخه خارجی را کنترل میکنیم.
And we are done with the program. Here is another example.
و کار برنامه تمام است.اینجا مثالی دیگرهست.
We will keep track of a list of list of numbers.
رد لیستی از اعداد را میخواهیم دنبال کنیم.
These are going to represent grades so for perhaps a student will have received a 70
قرار است که نمرات را نشان دهند شاید برای دانشجویی که در کلاسی نمره یکی 70
a 75 and an 80 in one class. And in another class that their are taking
یکی 75 و یکی 80 گرفته است.و در کلاس دیگری
they have a 70 an 80 a 90 and a 100. And in the third class they have an 80 and
یک 70ویک 80 و یک 90 و یک100 داریم.و در کلاس سوم یک 80 و
a 100. And, they want to know what the average is
یک نمره 100 گرفته است.و،میخواهند بدانند که برای
for each of these list of grades. We are going to write a function to
هر یک از این لیست نمرات میانگین چند است. میخواهیم تابعی بنویسیم که
calculate this list of averages. But before we do that we're going to start
لیس averages را محاسبه کند.ولی قبل از انجام این کار
with a similar problem. Just find the average of a list of
با مساله مشابهی شروع میکنیم.تنها میانگین لیست
numbers. So.
نمرات را پیدا کنید.پس.
Let's say that in one class, maybe English, the list of grades that we're
مثلا در یک کلاسی،چون کلاس زبان،لیست نمراتی را که
going to calculate the average of is 70, 75 and 80.
میخواهیم میانگینشان را محاسبه کنیم70و75و80 باشد.
In order to calculate the average of this, we need to go and add up all the
برای محاسبه میانگین آنها،لازم است که کلیه
assignment marks and then divide by how long that list is.
نمرات تکلیف را با هم جمع کرده و بر طول آن لیست تقسیم کنیم.
There's our accumulator, and then for each mark in English, what we're going to do is
جمع کننده ما که موجود است،و بعد برای هر نمره ای در زبان،کاری که باید بکنیم
we're going to add the mark to the total. Now,
جمع نمرات را به دست آوریم.حالا،
The total is 225. We need to divide that by the length of
مجموع آنها225 است.لازم است که آن را بر طول لیست تقسیم کنیم.
the list. Now that we know how to calculate the
اکنون میدانیم که چگونه
average of a list of numbers, we would like to do this for each of the lists in
میانگین لیستی از نمرات را محاسبه کنیم،این کار  برای تک تک لیست ها در لیست نمرات باید انجام شود
our grades list, and we would like to assemble the result into a list of these
و دوست داریم که نتایج این میانگین را در لیستی پشت هم اعلام کنیم.
averages. As we're developing this function, we need
همین طور که این تابع را میسازیم،نیاز به مثال است.
examples. The first example we're going to do is
اولین مثال که میخواهیم انجام دهیم
this list of grades that we have started with over on the left pane.
لیست نمراتی است که در پنجره سمت چپ این بالا شروع کردیم.
The average of 70, 75 and 80 is 75. The average of 70, 80, 90 and 100 is 85.
میانگین 70و75و80عدد75 است.میانگین 70و80و90و100 عدد 85 است.
The average of 80 and 100 is 90. All of these are floats.
میانگین 80و100میشود90.همه اینها اعداد اعشاری هستند.
Let's make this window just a little bit wider.
این پنجره را اندکی وسیعتر کنیم.
The pipe contract is next. What we have is a list of list of numbers.
بعد قرارداد لوله است.آنچه که داریم لیستی از لیست نمرات است.
Now, these are all integers. But we can certainly imagine giving
حالا،همه اینها اعداد صحیح هستند.ولی مطمئنا میتوانیم
floating point results for scores on a piece of work.
نتایج اعداد اعشاری را برای نمرات در بخشی از کار مجسم کنیم.
So, The pipe contract is going to be a list of
بنابراین قرارداد لوله لیستی از اعداد است.
lists of number. And that is the, the type of the
وآن،نوع پارامتر است.
parameter. And we are going to return a list of
و میخواهیم که لیستی از اعداد اعشاری تحویل دهیم.
float. We're fine with averages as the name, so
با میانگین ها به عنوان یک نام رابطه خوبی داریم،پس
we leave it as such, and we're going to take in maybe grades as the name of our
آن را این گونه ترک میکنیم،و شاید که نمرات را به عنوان
parameter. .
پارامتر بگیریم.
In our description, this is going to return a new list in which each item is
در توضیحات ما،قرار است که لیست جدیدی را تحویل دهد که آیتم های آن
the average of the grades in the inner list at the corresponding position.
میانگین نمرات لیست داخلی  در موقعیت مربوطه نمرات باشد.
. Of grades. Well, we know we're building a
خوب، میدانیم که داریم لیست جدیدی را میسازیم.
new list. And we're going to be doing this nested
و میخواهیم که این لیست تو در تو
list by nested list. So we're going to be accumulating this
با لیست تو در تو به انجام برسانیم.پس میخواهیم که این نتیجه را جمع آوری کنیم.
result. So we'll have maybe averages as the name
پس شاید که averagesرا به عنوان نام متغیرمان داشته باشیم
of our variable, which is going to be the list of averages at the end.
که در آخر کار لیست میانگین ها باشد.
And when we're done, we know we want to return averages.
و وقتی که کارمان تمام شد،میدانیم که میخواهیم میانگین را تحویل دهیم.
Well, we want to put into averages, the average of each of the lists inside our
خوب،میخواهیم میانگین ها را محاسبه کرده،میانگین هر لیست را در داخل
grades lists. So,
لیست نمرات خود قرار دهیم.بنابراین،
For each of the sub lists in the grades list, what we want to do is calculate the
برای هر کدام از زیر مجموعه لیست های نمرات،آن چه که میخواهیم انجام دهیم محاسبه
average of grades list and append it to averages.
میانگین لیست نمرات و ضمیمه ساختن آن به میانگین ها.
Well, we have code that does that over on the left.
خوب،برنامه ای داریم که در سمت چپ آنجا این کار را میکند.
We know that we want start total off at zero.
میدانیم که میخواهیم total را با صفر شروع کنیم.
And then for each mark in this particular sub grade list,
و آنگاه برای هر نمره ای در این زیرمجموعه لیست نمرات مشخص،
We would like to add it to total. And then once we are done with that,
به total میافزاییم.و وقتی که کارمان با آن تمام شد،
We will summon up the values on the grades list.
مقادیر را از لیست نمرات برمیداریم.
We would like to append to averages the average.
آن را به میانگین میانگین ها ضمیمه میکنیم.
And we're done. We will now call this in the visualizer
و کار تمام است.اکنون آن را در تجسم ساز فرا میخوانیم
and watch it execute. We have added two statements at the bottom
و پردازش آن را تحت نظر میگیریم.دو عبارت در ته فایل افزوده ایم.
of this file. The first one creates the, the nested
اولی لیست درون لیست رابه وجود آورده ،
list, And the second one calls the averages
و دومی توابع averages
function passing in that list. Let's visualize this.
را که در آن لیست مطرح میشوند را فرامیخواند.این را مجسم کنیم.
We first define our function. Next we are going to create about ten or
ابتدا تابع خود را تعریف میکنیم.آنگاه حدود ده تا سوژه به وجود میاوریم.
so objects. Grades refers to a list with three items
Grades به لیستی با سه آیتم در آن نظر دارد.
in it. The first one is a list with three items
اولی لیستی با سه آیتم
in it, 70, 75 and 80. The second one refer this to a list that
در آن 70و75و80 است.دومی به لست
has 70, 80, 90 and 100 in it. And the third item in index two in this
70و80و90و100 نظر دارد.و سومی با ضریب دو در لیست
outer list refers to a list with two items in it, 80 and 90.
بیرونی به لیست دو آیتمی 80و90.
This first nested list contains 70, 75, and 80.
اولین لیت داخل لیست شامل70و75و80 است.
The second nested list contains 70,80,90. Where is it?
دومین لیست داخل لیست شامل70و80و90 است.کجاست؟
90 and 100. This third nested list contains 80, and
90و100.این سومین لیست داخل لیست 80و100 را در خود دارد.
100. So indeed, the list structure that is
بنابراین،در واقع امر،ساختمان لیستی که
built in computer memory is a representation of what we have done on
در حافظه کامپیوتر ساخته شده نشانگر آن چه هست که در این سطر انجام داده ایم.
this line. Now we're going to pass that list into the
اکنون میخواهیم که آن لیست را از تابع averages گذر دهیم.
averages function. We'll get a stack frame for function
برای averages تابع چارچوب stack را به دست میاوریم که
averages containing parameter grades referring to that same list.
شامل پارامترهای نمرات است که به همان لیست نظر دارد.
We will start, here's a fun one, we will start a new variable averages that is an
شروع خواهیم کرد،اینجا fun one هست،متغیر averages جدیدی را شروع میکنیم که لیستی خالی است.
empty list. Notice we also have a function averages
توجه داشته باشید که تابع averages را هم در بیرون چرخه داریم.
outside. They're obviously two very different
واضح است که این دو چیز خیلی با هم تفاوت دارند.
things. Next we're going to go through this lists
آنگاه از این لیست خارج شده و وارد این لیست خارجی میشویم.
inside this outer list. So grades list is initially going to refer
بنابراین لیست نمرات در ابتدای کار نظر به
to the list that index at memory address x3.
که ضریب x3 را در لیست دارد.
Then we're going to go through 70, 75, and 80, add them up and divide by the length
آنگاه از 70و75و80 گذر کرده و آن ها را به هم افزوده و بر طول لیست تقسیم میکنیم.
of that list. We'll start total off at zero and for
total را با صفر شروع میکنیم و برای
every mark in the grades list, well mark is going to start off at 70 and the 75 and
هر نمره ای در لیست نمرات،و در هر دور گردشی در اینجا نمره از 70و75و80 شروع میشود.
then 80 each iteration here. We going to take that 70 here on line
میخواهیم که آن 70 را از اینجا روی سطر
seventeen and we're going to add it to the total which is zero.
هفدهم بگیریم و آن را به total که صفر باشد بیافزاییم.
So we'll get 70 of course 70 plus zero is zero.
پس 70 به دست میدهد البته که 70 به علاوه صفر باشد.
We will assign that to total. On this next iteration, we're going to
آن را برای total در نظر میگیریم.در دور گردش بعدی،
have the marquee as 75. Now we're going to take 75 and add it to
75 را داریم.اکنون 75 را میگیریم و به 70 اضافه میکنیم.
70. 70 plus 75 is 145.
70 بعلاوه 75 میشود 145.
And we will assign 145 to total. On the next iteration we're going to
و 145 برای total معلوم میشود.در دور گردش بعدی
assign the 80 to mark. That's what this four loop does.
نمره 80 را مطرح میکنیم.این کاری است که چرخه for انجام میدهد.
Grabs the last item in the list, mark now refers to 80.
آخرین آیتم لیست را ،که در اینجا نمره 80باشد را میگیرد.
On line seventeen we have an assignment statement. The right hand side evaluates
در سطر هفدهم عبارتی تکلیفی داریم.سمت راست
to 145 plus 80 or 225. We'll assign 225 to total.
145 به علاوه 80 یا 225 را ارزیابی میکند.225 میشود total.
We have now gone through all the items in that first nested list.
اکنون از همه آیتم های اولین لیست درون لیست گذر کرده ایم.
We've done the 70, the 75, and the 80, and so this for loop will now terminate.
کار 70و75و80 را تمام کردیم،و بنابراین این چرخه for اکنون پایان مییابد.
We will calculate 225 divided by the length of grades list, which is three, and
225 تقسیم بر طول لیست نمرات ،که 3 باشد،را محاسبه میکنیم و
we will append the result to the averages list.
نتیجه را به لیست averages ضمیمه میکنیم.
Now averages refers to a list containing 75.
اکنون averages به لیست شامل75 نظر دارد.
225 divided by three is 75. We have completed execution of the first
225 تقسیم بر3 میشود75.اولین دور گردش
iteration of the outer four loop. We will now, on this next iteration, get
چرخه بیرونی for را پایان دادیم.اکنون،در دور گردش بعدی،لیست دومی را بگیریم
the second list, with four items in it. Grades list now refers to that second
با چهار آیتمی که در آن هست.اکنون لیست نمرات به آن لیست دومی نظر دارد
list, with 70, 80, 90 and 100 in it. We will initialize total to zero,
با70و80و90و100 در آن.total را با صفر شروع میکنیم،
Reset it, and then we're going to go through the four numbers,
آن را ریست کنید، و آنگاه از چهار عدد گذر میکنیم،
Two, three, four and we're done. And now total is 340. The sum of 70 plus
دو،سه،چهار و کار تمام است.و اکنون total 340 است.مجموع 70 بعلاوه
80 plus 90 plus 100. We will append 340 divided by four to our
80 بعلاوه90 بعلاوه100.340تقسیم بر چهار را به لیست averages ضمیمه میکنیم.
averages list. And that happens to be 85.
و میشود 85.
And now for the third nested list. Grades list.
و اکنون سومین لیست درون لیست.لیستGrades.
The first of a list of two items in it, that's 80 and 100.
اولین لیست دو آیتم 80 و100 را داشت.
We'll reset total to zero. There's the 80 that we're dealing with.
total رابه صفر ریست میکنیم.الان80 را داریم.
Mark it now 80. We'll add 80 to zero, giving us 80, of
80 را به صفر اضافه میکنیم که میشود 80.
course. We will then get the 100.
بعد ممیرویم سراغ100.
And we'll add the two together. And then we will append 180 divided by the
و دو تا را به هم اضافه میکنیم.و سپس 180تقسیم بر
length of that nested list, or two. So 180 divided by two is 90.
طول این لیست درون لیست که دو باشد تقسیم کرده و ضمیمه میکنیم.
We have now gone through all three of our nested lists.
اکنون از هر سه لیست درون لیست گذر کرده ایم.
So this outer loop will terminate. And we're done.
به این ترتیب چرخه بیرونی پایان مییابد. و کار ما تمام شد.
We will now return, this averages list which as a reminder now contains 75, 85
اکنون لیت averages را تحویل میدهیم که ب75و85و
and 90. We have to return that value.
90 را شامل میشود.باید که آن مقدار را تحویل دهیم.
We don't do anything with it in the main program, so when I click forward, the
در برنامه اصلی کاری نمیکنیم،بنابراین،وقتی که کلیک میکنم،
program will just end.
برنامه خاتمه مییابد.